Finding Aid for Michigan Dental Association records, 1856-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Dental Association records 1856-2006
Michigan Dental Association.
4 oversize volumes
4 linear feet
861060 Bf 2
Formerly the Michigan State Dental Association. Minute books and subject files relating to its activities; also scrapbooks of association's women's auxiliary.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records came from four different sources: from the U-M School of Dentistry Library (donor no. 764 ), Dr. Marcus L. Ward (donor no. 3472 ), from the Michigan Dental Association (donor no. 7480 ), and from the Women’s Auxiliary of the MDA (donor no. 7933 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Dental Association was founded in 1856 through the efforts of two Detroit dentists, Hiram Benedict and Lorrain Christopher Whiting. The Society was conceived as a vehicle through which professional standards could be raised through exchanges of information. During the Civil War, discussion and debate was supplemented by the practice of holding clinics, allowing for demonstrations. Supply houses also began to send representatives to meetings, in order to demonstrate their products.
The Association's efforts to raise professional standards inevitably led it to be interested in dental education. The society was instrumental to the founding of a dental school at the University of Michigan in 1875, and for almost a quarter of a century thereafter maintained a visiting committee which come to Ann Arbor to monitor the school's progress. Efforts to guarantee professionalism in dentistry also led the Association to seek legislation regulating dentists. The Association first achieved this goal in 1883 when the state legislature passed a law establishing a dental licensing board.
Around the turn of the century the once dynamic organization had begun to show signs of stagnation. A determined effort by several members between 1906 and 1908 led to a complete reorganization of the body, as well as to renewed interest and life. In 1920 the Association's membership first passed 1,000. The organization's basic goal continued to be the professionalization and advancement of dentistry through education and regulation.
For a complete history of the organization, the researcher should consult Robert M. Warner Profile of A Profession: A History of the Michigan State Dental Association (Detroit: Wayne State University Press, 1964).
The records of the Michigan Dental Association includes minute books and subject files relating to its activities and scrapbooks of association's women's auxiliary. The records are divided into four series: Administrative files; Minute books of Annual Meetings; Minutes of Board of Trustees; and Scrapbooks of the women's auxiliary of the organization.
Subjects:
Dentistry--Michigan.; Dentists--Michigan.; Michigan Dental Association.; Michigan Dental Association. Women's Auxiliary.; Michigan State Dental Association.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Michigan Dental Association. Women's Auxiliary.; Women--Organizations.
Contributors:
Ward, Marcus Llewellyn, 1875-1963.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Administrative files
  - Constitution and By-laws (including Code of Ethics)
    - Text 1886-1907 (Box 1)
    - Committee 1948-1962, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Convention
    - 1930 1931 (Box 1)
    - 1935 1936 (Box 1)
    - 1938 (Box 1)
    - 1939 (Box 1)
    - 1959 (Box 1)
  - Dental Education, Committee on
    - 1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1970 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Executive Council 1937 (Box 1)
  - Health Education, Council on 1942-1948 (Box 1)
  - History by Walter McBride (1912-1917), written in 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Incorporation Papers 1876-1958 (Box 1)
  - Legislation, Ad Hoc Committee to Develop 1971 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1950s-1960s (Box 1)
  - "Official Record," 1856-1903 (Box 1)
  - Orthodontic Costs 1943 (Box 1)
  - Public Relations Committee 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - Survey Coordinating Committee 1977-1979 (Box 1)
- Minute books of Annual Meetings
  - 1856-1880 (Box 1)
  - 1881-1904 (Box 1)
  - 1905-1923 (Box 2)
  - 1924-1927 (Box 2)
  - 1928-1933 (Box 2)
  - 1934-1938 (Box 2)
  - 1939-1950 (Box 2)
  - 1951-1956 (Box 2)
- Minutes of Board of Trustees
  - 1956-1987, 6 folders; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - 1987-2006, 2 folders; 17 folders (Box 4)
  - Microfiche of minute books of annual meetings 1856-1956 and of board of trustees, 1956-1988 (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks
  - Women's Auxiliary of the Michigan Dental Association 1946-1980 (Volume 1)
    (include photographs)
  - Women's Auxiliary of the Michigan Dental Association 1946-1980 (Volume 2)
    (continued)
  - Women's Auxiliary of the Michigan Dental Association 1946-1980 (Volume 3)
  - Women's Auxiliary of the Michigan Dental Association 1946-1980 (Volume 4)